As a very general overview,
when we're talking about
training for hypertrophy,
we're typically looking at something
like 8 to 12 repetitions per set.
Now, in the last five to eight years,
it has become extremely clear,
hypertrophy happens pretty equally
from as low as five repetitions per set
all the way up to 30 repetitions per set.
So you can go anywhere in that window
as long as you're training
to the same effort
and expect equal hypertrophy.
But that said, most of the time,
most people stick closer to
kind of 8 to 12 repetitions,
but by all means, go lower or higher
and it should be no problem at all,
absolutely equally effective.
What that means then in terms of intensity
is that will scale based upon
how heavy you're lifting.
Generally, if you're in
the kind of 8 to 12 repetition range,
you're probably in the 70 to 80%
of your one-rep max range.
If you were to go to a little bit lower,
say five, six repetitions per set,
you might be a little bit
higher, maybe 80, 85%.
And if you're to go lower,
in fact, you can go as low as 30%
of your one-repetition maximum.
That's been shown
extensively in the research,
equally effective,
but that would just
require you to do 25 or 30
or potentially even more
repetitions per set.
I've talked about the
pros and cons of this
in other episodes
and potentially will even next
season go into the details.
They are not the same
because of things like strength.
So while you'll expect equal hypertrophy
with, say, 25 repetitions per set
as you would with eight
repetitions per set,
the strength progress
will not be the same.
Strength needs to happen
at a lower rep range
so that you can get the intensity
of the load high enough.
Typically what we're looking
at there is, of course,
what I've spoken of before,
the three to five method,
so three to five repetitions per set,
but that could go a little bit higher.
Really do remember, these
are not hard cutoff lines.
These are just kind of phased out.
So if I can get strength at
five repetitions per set,
what do you think happens at six?
Still some strength.
What about seven?
Yeah, still some.
Eight? Yeah, sure.
But what about at 30?
Well, okay, very little.
And so what happens is
it's just kind of like
where is the general place to be
most of the time?
That's all we're saying with strength.
But because of what we're trying to do,
reach a high load,
we have to have a low repetitions per set
because fatigue starts to reduce
the amount of weight we can actually lift.
So strength is generally something, again,
like three to five
repetitions, plus or minus.
Can be as low as one.
If you want to truly peak strength,
you do one repetition as heavy as you can.
There's cons to that as well.
You want to go a little bit higher,
five, six, seven reps,
okay, still fine,
but maybe you have to
go a little bit lighter.
Gives you rough context
of what you're looking at.
For power, just continue
that logic one more step.
So because power has a strength
and velocity component,
not only can I not afford
to lose some force output,
I can't afford to lose velocity either.
And so power happens typically
in a similar rep range,
almost always though less
than kind of six reps per set at the most,
usually even less than that, right?
Two to five, probably more
so even than strength,
and we have to do it at a fast speed.
So the intensity,
the load can't be as high
'cause I have to move it fast, okay?
So while you could do something like this,
say three sets of three repetitions
at 95% of your bench press for strength,
that's going to move very slow,
and so that wouldn't be
great at developing power.
We would want to go to maybe
three sets of three repetitions at 65%.
So not super, super light,
'cause now we're just
working on pure speed,
but not super heavy either
because now we're just
working on pure force.
Somewhere in the middle.
Every exercise has a
different optimal load,
in other words, how heavy you can lift,
what percentage of your
one-rep max to maximize power.
Generally, very generally,
upper body smaller exercises
tend to achieve their peak
power at a lighter percentage,
40% of your max, 50% of your max,
maybe as low as 30% of your max.
Bigger exercises like a squat,
higher, maybe 50% of your
max, 60% of your max.
More complicated movements
like a snatch or a clean and jerk
can even be as high as like
80 to 95% of your one-rep max.
So it does vary a little bit,
but the point with power always is
it has to be a combination
of heavy and fast.
If it's fast and no load,
it's speed but not power,
which is okay too if
that's what you're after.
If it's heavy and very, very slow,
it's force, which is okay,
but it's not power either.
Power needs to be somewhere in the middle.
So with that in mind, then,
the rest range for hypertrophy
can really be whatever you'd like.
It can be as small as 30 seconds.
Now, by doing that, you're going
to accumulate more fatigue,
which means you're either going
to have to do less repetitions
or less weight or a combination,
but that's absolutely fine.
It can be high rest.
Even up to five minutes of rest
have been shown to produce
equal hypertrophy as 30 seconds.
Obviously, if you go more
rest, you get more recovery,
which means we now need
to keep the weight high or go higher
and keep the rep range high or go higher.
And so pros and cons, there
are subtle differences,
but equal benefit from short rest ranges
as low as 30 seconds
all the way up to longer rest
ranges up to five minutes.
For strength and power though,
it's a different story.
You need to stay away for the most part
of low rest intervals.
Remember, this is all about quality.
We need to practice moving
fast a bunch of times.
heavy a bunch of times.
If we shorten our rest intervals
and we can't move as fast
and we can't produce as much force,
then we're not practicing producing force
and we're not practicing moving faster,
and so we're really
undercutting our adaptations.
Two to five minutes of rest
is the rough recommendation
for power and strength,
but you do want to think
about this in context.
If I were to do, say, one vertical jump,
I don't truly need to rest five minutes.
That's not that fatiguing.
I could probably honestly do one minute
and depending on how fit you are,
you might even be able to do,
like, 40 seconds and be fine.
And so they're just guidelines, okay?
Think about the person,
think about what phase
of training they're in.
Early in a training phase,
maybe you want more rest,
but 16 weeks into a training program,
you're very fit, you're very
strong, you're in shape,
you maybe don't necessarily need
a full extensive rest interval
to produce peak power again, okay?
If you're trying to maximize,
truly maximize your strength,
you're probably going to take
five-plus minutes of rest.
If you're trying to work on a
lot of different repetitions,
on a lot of exercises of power,
maybe two minutes is good.
Five, oftentimes when I
say that people are like,
"Oh my god, five whole minutes?"
And they go to the gym, they do it,
they start their clock
and like 30 seconds in
they're like, "Oh my gosh.
Like, I have to wait
another 4 1/2 minutes?"
Well, not necessarily all the time
and not for every exercise.
I will caution though,
you are not nearly as
recovered as you think you are.
If you're used to doing things
that are like moderate strength
or hypertrophy or muscular endurance,
you're not really understanding
and you typically can't register
what it feels like to be at 100%.
You get to kind of 90, 92% and you think,
"Yeah, yeah, I don't feel any difference."
In this particular case,
if we're trying to maximize
power and strength,
that last 7% matters,
but you may not be able to perceive it
if you're not used to it.
And so typically what I would say
is if you're not used to
this type of training,
I would still take more rest intervals
than you think you want to.
What's the harm?
You cost yourself an extra six minutes
combined at the end of the workout
by doing 20 more seconds of rest?
Okay, you can live with that, okay?
If eventually you realize that's enough
and you want to back it
back down, that's great,
but initially start off with
more rest than you think.
For the most part,
people err on the side of too short
when it comes to power and strength,
not necessarily too long.
[music]